In 1162
deep in the heart of Asia, a child was
born. He was clutching a blood clot, a
sign from heaven that he was destined to
be a great warrior.
His life was to become a legend. His
name Genghis Kh.
[screaming]
Many believe his story is simple. That
he was the incarnation of evil. A brutal
[music] barbarian who butchered
millions.
[screaming]
But the real character of Genghask Khan
is far more intriguing.
How did this illiterate outcast turn the
feuding tribes of Mongolia into a
powerful nation?
And how did he transform the Mongol
hordes into a ruthless and disciplined
fighting machine?
An army with revolutionary tactics and
ingenious weapons that ultimately stood
poised to conquer Europe.
And why on his deathbed did he believe
his divine mission remained unfulfilled?
>> Soon I will know death, but I will never
know my destiny.
>> Shortly after his death, his heirs
gathered their memories into an epic
account of his life. They called it the
secret history of the Mongols.
Evidence from Chinese and Persian
sources, the work of leading scholars
and the secret history allow this to be
the most complete television portrait of
Genghis Khan ever made.
The characters are all real historical
figures and the words of Genghis Khan
are rooted in the great speeches of the
secret history.
This is the story of how that tiny fist
turned to iron and came to rule the
largest [music] land empire ever known
to man.
In 1215,
the Mongol warrior Genghis Khn led his
army to Beijing, capital of northern
China.
After fighting his way across Asia, the
city stood before him.
But Beijing was protected by formidable
defenses. Surrounding it was a wall 12 m
high and 30 km long. Behind the wall was
one of the world's most advanced armies.
>> [screaming]
>> First, Genghis Khan besieged the city.
>> Then, he ordered an audacious attack. He
forced enemy prisoners to fill his front
lines.
He built new weapons to attack the
city's defenses.
>> Finally, having endured the Chinese
arrows and bombs, he commanded his
Mongol warriors to scale the walls.
Genghis Khan sensed victory was within
his grasp.
Beijing was fighting for its life.
A poor nomad from the remote Mongol
step.
Genghish Khan had made an extraordinary
journey.
The boy who had become Genghask Khan was
called Teujin.
He was the son of a tribal warrior
chief.
When he was only 9 years old, he
received news that was to change his
life.
>> My father had been poisoned by a rival
tribe.
>> [snorts]
>> My mother told me my father's enemies
were forever the enemies of my own
heart.
>> From that day,
I would never be a child again.
As the eldest son, Teigjin grew up to
lead what was little more than an
extended family.
>> And on the steps, a small tribe was weak
and vulnerable.
To survive, Teigjin knew he must forge
links with other tribes, and there was
only one way he could do that.
>> Her name
was Borte.
>> There were only two things to know about
my marriage.
She
>> was a woman of beauty,
>> and the sable fur they gave us
>> was worth a thousand of the swiftest
horses.
The great tribes of Mongolia were locked
in a spiral of murderous vendettas.
There was only one law on the steps.
If a man wanted something, he took it.
Now, Teigjin had something another
[music] man wanted.
>> The Marit tribe had feuded with
Teigjin's father.
>> Now, Teigjin himself was in danger,
[cheering]
>> and especially vulnerable was his new
wife. [cheering]
>> [screaming]
>> Stop.
The secret history recurs what Teigjin,
the man who would one day be Genghish
Khan, did next.
They had taken my wife. I knew what I
had to do.
>> What Teigjin had to do was to escape.
>> [screaming]
>> Only a fool
fights a battle he knows he cannot win.
Wife stealing was common on the steps.
Borte knew she had no choice but to
submit.
I had just one friend I could trust.
Jamuka.
As children, we had sworn the vow of
Ander.
It was the most sacred vow of all.
We were blood brothers.
A bond that joined our lives as one.
With my sworn brother Jamuka, my power
had been increased by heaven and earth.
At the Markit camp in the mountains of
northern Mongolia, Teigjin went looking
for his wife.
[screaming]
>> [screaming]
[cheering]
>> We made the merketss pay for their
[cheering] deed.
We destroyed their families and emptied
their breasts.
>> Teujin, the man who was to become
Genghish Khan, was barely 20 and he'd
already eliminated one of Mongolia's
great tribes.
In those early days, Teujin and Jamuka
shared the leadership of the tribe.
>> Yet, even as they celebrated the victory
over the Marits, there was a hidden
tension between them.
>> At the root was a fundamental [music]
question.
How to measure a man's worth?
Both Tein and Jamuka were the sons of
tribal leaders, Mongolian aristocrats.
But only Teujin had experienced a
childhood of real adversity and learned
from it.
Now I cared only for the strength in a
man's heart.
A warrior does not win a battle by
virtue of his birth.
Teojin rewarded ability and loyalty
alone.
One of his most promising warriors was
Subday, the son of a humble herd.
But this attitude flew in the face of
Mongol tradition.
Jamama's noble birth led him to believe
that high rank should be reserved only
for Mongol aristocrats.
>> But now his blood brother was throwing
out the [music] old ways.
>> The gulf between Tejin and Jamuka widens
still further until the prophecy of the
Mongol holy man brought their
relationship to a crisis.
As she shaman said, he had ascended into
heaven in a holy trance where the
supreme god told him that he would give
to me and to my sons
the whole surface of the world
>> for the tribe and for Jamoka.
>> It was a decisive moment.
Men who are sworn brothers share one
life. But I began to question whether
Jamuka was truly my blood brother for
all eternity.
for
two.
It was not right that our differences
should force a feud. But my wife stopped
me from going after him.
She warned that one day my blood brother
would ride against me.
the Teigin. This feud brought back the
darkest memory of his childhood.
I knew where a war between brothers
would lead.
Even when we were starving, my brother
Bector had betrayed us. He refused to
share the spoils of a hunt.
He died of his wounds.
>> Jamukha split the tribe.
Two years would pass before they would
hear from him.
High on the plateau of central Mongolia
is a place known as Dalan Balu.
It was here that Borte's prophecy would
be fulfilled.
Jamukha ambushed Teujin's tribe.
Teujin, the man who would be Genghish
Khan, led an army that was unprepared,
outnumbered, and outwitted.
It had been a catastrophic defeat,
but there was worse to follow.
Jamoka took the generals he had captured
and subjected them to the crulest of
punishments.
He boiled them alive.
When Teigan learned of the atrocity, he
made this vow.
>> By the power of heaven, I swore to gain
my vengeance. Never again would I be
defeated,
nor my loyal warriors so dishonored.
It was now that Teojin started a
revolution.
>> They say that the Mongols were descended
from THE WOLF.
[screaming]
>> Like the wolf,
we were famous for our ferocity and
courage.
But to win a battle, we had to fight
fiercely.
Not as individual warriors,
but as parts of a whole
teen formed an elite officer training
corps, the Kashik.
He was building a professional fighting
machine from top to bottom.
The Mongols universal instrument of
battle was the bow. Made from wood and
animal bone, it had a shooting range of
500 m.
Training in archery [music] and
horsemanship was made compulsory for
all, even children. They learned to
release their arrows at the exact moment
the hor's hooves were off the ground for
maximum accuracy.
Tein had thrown out the old tribal
divisions.
This was a meritocracy.
[cheering] This was a modern army.
Now he was ready.
In the summer of 124,
Teigjin rode west to confront his blood
brother.
The outcome would be decisive for the
future of the Mongol people.
In the foothills of the Heni Mountains
on the eve of battle, Teigjin called his
generals to him.
I told them
one tribe was like a single arrow easily
broken,
>> but many tribes together would be
strong.
They could never be broken.
Stop. [screaming]
[cheering]
But Terjin didn't just rely on
inspirational speeches. He practiced
psychological warfare.
>> I knew Jamaica's scouts would be
watching as my men prepared for battle.
I ordered each man to light not one but
five fires.
>> Jamoka's scout reported that Tejin's
army was so large they had [music] more
fires than there were stars in the sky.
>> [screaming and cheering]
>> At daybreak, Jamoka led his army onto
the heights of Chakim Magut.
And this was the site that confronted
him.
I saw the man who had been my friend,
who had sworn the sacred vow of Andy,
but he had broken that vow.
Jamoka was about to become the first
commander to face an army that would
eventually conquer 12 million square
miles.
machine target.
We advanced in silence, saving our
battle cries to the last.
When the enemy came within reach, my
archers released a storm of arrows.
And my cavalry attacked without mercy.
[cheering]
According
[screaming]
[groaning]
to the secret history, each tactic was
Meticulously planned and ingenious,
Teigin held squadrons and weapons in
reserve.
Then with the enemy in disarray, they
regrouped and charged.
One of Teigjin's cavalry squadrons
suddenly fled the battlefield.
Jamaku's men chased them down, but they
were being lured into a trap.
>> [screaming]
>> In the heart of the battle, Jamaica saw
his army destroyed and he ran.
Across the battlefield,
I saw the bodies of Jamaka's men lying
together like felled logs in a forest.
Following the defeat, Jamaica fled into
the mountains of Tanu.
He hid throughout the winter of 124.
In the spring, he reappeared, escorted
by two of his own generals, who thought
they knew where their best interests
lay.
They delivered Jamoka to Teigan.
The generals expected a reward for
betraying their leader and delivering
him into the hands of his enemy.
And I saw they got their reward.
I'm doing it.
Tinker.
You push
You're
How are you?
Tein granted his [music] blood brother
his final wish
and broke his back.
The defeat and death of Jamoka led to a
sight [music] never before seen in the
history of Mongolia.
The recognition of one man as the leader
of all the Mongol tribes.
In the Mongol world, there had never
been such a figure.
And in 126, a new title was created to
honor him.
>> Universal King,
>> ruler of all men,
>> Genghis Kh.
But my destiny, the destiny of the great
Mongol people, was still unfulfilled.
>> Genghask Khan had forged a nation. But
now he faced a new and more potent
threat, China. He knew the Chinese would
not tolerate such a powerful leader as
him on their border.
So he took the fight to them.
In a campaign that was to last 6 years,
he led his army of 50,000 Mongols on one
of the most audacious military actions
in history.
He crossed the Gobi Desert
and invaded northern China.
On hearing that the Mongol army was
approaching, the emperor of North China
[music] sent this message.
Our empire is as vast as the sea.
Yours is but a handful of [music] sand.
How can we fear you?
The Chinese had spent centuries
perfecting their defenses. But Genghis
Khan solved the problem posed by China's
biggest border defense, the Great Wall,
by one simple expedient. They went
around it.
The Chinese were the richest and most
civilized people in the East, but they
also knew how to fight a dirty war.
Iron spikes, like medieval minefields,
were buried in the path of the oncoming
Mongol armies.
Get up.
The Chinese could afford to employ
people to fight for
in the borderlands. The Mongols met a
force of heavily armed mercenaries.
Who were loyal as only mercenaries could
be.
Reinforced by the mercenary troops, they
marched into the fertile plains of
northern China.
Few of the Chinese villagers had seen a
Mongol warrior before.
And few of the Mongols would have
journeyied this far into China.
It was the clash of two alien cultures.
There was only one certainty. The
Chinese would never forget them.
>> [screaming]
>> The Mongols plundered without mercy. And
from each conquest, Genghis Khan took
his own reward, a highborn wife from the
vanquished.
>> The greatest fortune a man can have is
to conquer his enemy, steal his riches,
ride his horses, and enjoy his women.
>> Further east lay an even greater prize.
With a population of 350,000,
13th century Beijing was one of the most
sophisticated cities on Earth.
Capital of the Northern Chinese Empire,
famous for its grand palaces, gilded
temples, and markets overflowing with
silks and spices.
In his quest to take these riches for
himself, Genghis Khan faced one huge
problem. Standing between him and the
conquest of the city was a wall.
12 m high and 30 km long with 900 guard
towers.
To a nomadic army used to fighting on
the open steps, these fortifications
seemed impregnable. I'd trained my men
to attack with the speed of the wind.
Now they had to learn the guile of the
wolf.
>> His first tactic was straightforward.
He waited. The Mongols set up camp
outside the city and stopped supplies
from getting in.
From Chinese engineers who had defected,
his generals learned to build catapults,
portable defenses, and [music] battering
rams, the tools of siege warfare.
[music]
>> The Mongols were in no hurry.
They feasted on the supplies they
captured.
>> Genghis Khan turned Beijing into a
prison.
Within the walls, thousands starved to
death.
The survivors resorted to cannibalism.
[music]
Finally, Genghask Khn's army was ready
to attack.
All who surrender would be spared. Those
who did not surrender, but opposed with
struggle and dissension,
would be annihilated.
Despite enduring months of starvation,
the commander of the Chinese army still
controlled a formidable garrison with
thousands of men and a powerful array of
weapons.
>> [screaming]
>> Genghask Khan knew that few in the first
wave of the attack would survive.
So he forced captured enemy prisoners to
wheel the siege engines forward into the
killing zone. [screaming]
It is said that each of his own warriors
was given a silk shirt.
[screaming]
If the arrow penetrated the body, it
took the silk with it, making it easier
to draw the arrow out and minimizing the
wound. [screaming]
>> [screaming]
[cheering]
[groaning]
>> What the [__]
But despite the Mongols attempts to
master siege warfare, the Chinese were
still much more advanced in their
military technology.
They responded by filling bombs with
crude oil, molten metal, chemicals, and
excrement.
[screaming]
Despite the ferocious bombardment,
Genghis Khan ordered his men to advance
to the walls.
Once again, Chinese prisoners were in
the front line. [cheering]
Heat.
[cheering]
[screaming]
Heat.
>> [screaming]
>> As the city fell, the Chinese commander
had just one option.
[cheering]
>> [cheering]
>> Genghis Khan was so confident of victory
that he left his army to capture the
city. [cheering]
His final command to his generals was to
fulfill his prophecy.
He ordered total annihilation.
For one month, his army plundered,
burnt, and raped.
A year later, visiting foreign
ambassadors described the streets as
slippery with human fat.
They also recorded that beyond the walls
stood an entire mountain of bones.
Genghask Khan's fearsome reputation grew
from the destruction and carnage he
practiced in Beijing. But what he now
created at Kakorum [music] in central
Mongolia revealed an entirely different
nature.
Genghis Khn wanted Kakorum to be a great
trading and cultural center.
>> Here in stark contrast to his nomadic
origins, he began to establish a
permanent capital and he wanted his
people to benefit from his conquests.
>> My people were as numerous as the trees
in a forest. I wanted them to feed on
tender meat, live in beautiful tents,
and pasture their horses on rich soil.
To achieve this, he imported knowledge.
He learned the technology of the Chinese
military.
He established a medical corps trained
by Chinese physicians.
He ordered his followers to create a
record of all his rules and all his
judgments.
>> It was forbidden for any man [music] to
own a Mongol slave
and each tribe was given its own grazing
[music] grounds.
It was the beginning of a legal system.
The Mongols could neither read nor
write, but Genghaskhan understood the
power of the written word.
Above all, he wanted his legacy
recorded.
[clears throat]
in.
>> He looked to the west to build on his
conquests, not through war,
>> but through trade. He sent ambassadors
to Persia and established a network of
routes linked by staging posts 40 km
apart.
>> A messenger could travel 200 km in a
single day.
It was a medieval pony express.
In the summer of 1218,
one messenger [music] sent back to
Genghis Khan from Persia carried a
package. A package that would change the
course of history.
was the head of Genghis Khan's
ambassador.
>> The Sultan had fundamentally misjudged
Genghish Khan's character.
>> Genghaskhan sent an army 200,000 strong
to invade Persia.
It was a campaign of extreme savagery.
>> I was not the instigator of these
tribulations.
God grant me the [music] strength to
exact vengeance.
On his order, every Persian town that
did not submit was burnt to the ground.
When they had finished, over a million
men, women, and children were dead.
After the conquest of Persia,
Genghaskhan ordered a small army to see
how far west they could penetrate before
they were stopped. And they weren't
stopped at all.
This was the Mongols first raid into
Europe. It would not be their last. His
empire was now four times the size of
Alexander the Great and twice the size
of the Roman Empire.
But even this was not enough to satisfy
the desire of Genghish Khan. He wanted
something more, something his army could
not give him. Which is why in 1222
this man traveled towards Genghaskhan's
court. He was a revered Tauist monk.
from him. Genghask Khan sought just one
thing.
>> I told him how my life was a divine
mission.
I've been sent to Earth to conquer the
world.
I spoke of the prophecies, the battles,
my ambitions, my aims.
I asked what medicine he had brought to
prolong my earthly existence.
>> It was only then the monk realized
Genghask Khan was asking for the secret
elixia of eternal life.
>> Unfortunately, the monk could only offer
him advice about prolonging life through
sexual abstinence but not immortality.
There is nothing to indicate that
Genghask Khan took [music] the monk's
advice. Recent scientific evidence
suggests that perhaps one in 200 men
alive today can trace their genetic
lineage to Genghask Khan.
Four years later, he embarked on one
more campaign of conquest into China.
Hson.
[snorts]
According
to legend, these were the last words of
Genghask Khan.
>> I have conquered for you.
>> A large empire,
[snorts] but my life was too short to
take the whole world.
That
>> I leave to you.
He appointed his son [music] Agade to
succeed him as Khan.
Genghask Khan died without having
achieved what he believed was his
destiny
to conquer the entire world.
In the years after his death, his sons
carried out his wish doubling the size
[music] of the empire.
They returned to Europe and invaded
Russia, Poland, and Hungary.
But in 1242, approaching Vienna, the new
Khn died.
Mongol law decreed that all chiefs
returned to elect a new leader, and
Europe was spared the Mongol terror.
[music]
A century later, his mighty empire began
to crumble.
His
reputation has made him one of history's
immortals.
A reputation enhanced by the mystery of
his burial.
It is said that every witness to his
funeral cortees was executed to keep the
sight of the tomb a secret.
Today, almost 8 centuries later, the
burial place of Genghis Khn remains
undiscovered.
There is no grave, no morselum,
no monument to this bloodthirsty
conqueror, the most successful military
commander the world has ever known.
>> [music]
>> Heat.